<window anim_hint="htranslate" text="auto_adjust_size">
  <list_view x="0"  y="0" w="100%" h="-50" default_item_height="60">
    <scroll_view name="view" x="0"  y="0" w="-12" h="100%">
      <list_item h="128" style="odd_clickable" children_layout="default(r=1,c=0)" auto_adjust_size="true">
        <image draw_type="icon" w="30" image="earth"/>
        <label w="-30" auto_adjust_size="true">
    <property name="text">
大江东去，浪淘尽，千古风流人物。
故垒西边，人道是，三国周郎赤壁。
乱石穿空，惊涛拍岸，卷起千堆雪。
江山如画，一时多少豪杰。
遥想公瑾当年，小乔初嫁了，雄姿英发。
羽扇纶巾，谈笑间，樯橹灰飞烟灭。
故国神游，多情应笑我，早生华发。
人生如梦，一尊还酹江月。
    </property>
        </label>
      </list_item>
      <list_item h="128" style="even_clickable" children_layout="default(c=1,r=0)" auto_adjust_size="true">
        <image draw_type="icon" h="30" image="earth"/>
        <label h="-30" auto_adjust_size="true">
    <property name="text">
蒹葭苍苍，白露为霜。所谓伊人，在水一方。
溯洄从之，道阻且长；溯游从之，宛在水中央。
蒹葭凄凄，白露未晞[1]。所谓伊人，在水之湄。
溯洄从之，道阻且跻；溯游从之，宛在水中坻。
蒹葭采采，白露未已，所谓伊人，在水之涘[2]。
溯洄从之，道阻且右；溯游从之，宛在水中沚
    </property>
        </label>
      </list_item>
      <list_item h="128" style="odd_clickable" auto_adjust_size="true">
        <image draw_type="icon" x="r:10" y="m" w="30" h="30" image="earth"/>
        <label h="100%" w="100%" auto_adjust_size="true">
    <property name="text">
长恨歌

【作者】白居易 【朝代】唐

汉皇重色思倾国，御宇多年求不得。

杨家有女初长成，养在深闺人未识。

天生丽质难自弃，一朝选在君王侧。

回眸一笑百媚生，六宫粉黛无颜色。

春寒赐浴华清池，温泉水滑洗凝脂。

侍儿扶起娇无力，始是新承恩泽时。

云鬓花颜金步摇，芙蓉帐暖度春宵。

春宵苦短日高起，从此君王不早朝。

承欢侍宴无闲暇，春从春游夜专夜。

后宫佳丽三千人，三千宠爱在一身。

金屋妆成娇侍夜，玉楼宴罢醉和春。

姊妹弟兄皆列土，可怜光彩生门户。

遂令天下父母心，不重生男重生女。

骊宫高处入青云，仙乐风飘处处闻。

缓歌慢舞凝丝竹，尽日君王看不足。

渔阳鼙鼓动地来，惊破霓裳羽衣曲。

九重城阙烟尘生，千乘万骑西南行。

翠华摇摇行复止，西出都门百余里。

六军不发无奈何，宛转蛾眉马前死。

花钿委地无人收，翠翘金雀玉搔头。

君王掩面救不得，回看血泪相和流。

黄埃散漫风萧索，云栈萦纡登剑阁。

峨嵋山下少人行，旌旗无光日色薄。

蜀江水碧蜀山青，圣主朝朝暮暮情。

行宫见月伤心色，夜雨闻铃肠断声。

天旋地转回龙驭，到此踌躇不能去。

马嵬坡下泥土中，不见玉颜空死处。

君臣相顾尽沾衣，东望都门信马归。

归来池苑皆依旧，太液芙蓉未央柳。

芙蓉如面柳如眉，对此如何不泪垂。

春风桃李花开夜，秋雨梧桐叶落时。

西宫南苑多秋草，落叶满阶红不扫。

梨园弟子白发新，椒房阿监青娥老。

夕殿萤飞思悄然，孤灯挑尽未成眠。

迟迟钟鼓初长夜，耿耿星河欲曙天。

鸳鸯瓦冷霜华重，翡翠衾寒谁与共。

悠悠生死别经年，魂魄不曾来入梦。

临邛道士鸿都客，能以精诚致魂魄。

为感君王辗转思，遂教方士殷勤觅。

排空驭气奔如电，升天入地求之遍。

上穷碧落下黄泉，两处茫茫皆不见。

忽闻海上有仙山，山在虚无缥渺间。

楼阁玲珑五云起，其中绰约多仙子。

中有一人字太真，雪肤花貌参差是。

金阙西厢叩玉扃，转教小玉报双成。

闻道汉家天子使，九华帐里梦魂惊。

揽衣推枕起徘徊，珠箔银屏迤逦开。

云鬓半偏新睡觉，花冠不整下堂来。

风吹仙袂飘飖举，犹似霓裳羽衣舞。

玉容寂寞泪阑干，梨花一枝春带雨。

含情凝睇谢君王，一别音容两渺茫。

昭阳殿里恩爱绝，蓬莱宫中日月长。

回头下望人寰处，不见长安见尘雾。

惟将旧物表深情，钿合金钗寄将去。

钗留一股合一扇，钗擘黄金合分钿。

但教心似金钿坚，天上人间会相见。

临别殷勤重寄词，词中有誓两心知。

七月七日长生殿，夜半无人私语时。

在天愿作比翼鸟，在地愿为连理枝。

天长地久有时尽，此恨绵绵无绝期。
    </property>
        </label>
      </list_item>
      <list_item h="128" style="even_clickable" auto_adjust_size="true">
        <label h="100%" w="100%" auto_adjust_size="true" line_wrap="true">
          <property name="text">
Tang Emperor Xuanzhong lusted after a beauty worthy of taking a country to war for,
For so many years of his reign, unfulfilled his wish remained.
There was a Yang family whose daughter had come of age,
She was well kempt in her boudoir unknown to the social scene.
Yet her natural beauty had spelt her destiny that could not be forsaken,
Into the palace she did go and by the Emperor's side she was received.
As she turned her head, one smile enchanted all,
Outshining all women in the Palace who in comparison had their colour lost.
In spring chill, the Emperor bestowed on her a bath in the Splendid Pond,
A natural thermal spa with salubrious waters to her milky skin cleanse;
A maid helped to support her lady-like delicacy,
Thus began the Emperor's adoration of this fair lady.
She had a florid face and cloud-soft hair adorned with glittering golden beads that swayed,
Behind bedchamber curtains painted with lotus, springtime passion was in play;
Springtime passion made speed of night and in no time the sun had risen high,
The Emperor stopped attending the morning assembly on state affairs.
Pleasing the Emperor and accompanying him at banquets took up all of her time,
Springtime is for garden wayfaring and the night-time for bedchamber private affairs.
The Emperor's beauty mansions held three thousand fair ladies,
Whom the Emperor could have adored but he chose to dote on Lady Yang alone.
In her gilded chamber she prepared for the Emperor's night entertainment,
After a banquet on a majestic pavilion she'd waver down in sensual high.
All of her brothers and sisters were awarded with prominent official titles,
All the power and glory because of her on one family fell.
Hence all fathers and mothers of the world,
Would rather than boys girls bear and raise.
The Li Palace soared into the sky among clouds,
From there heavenly music drifted in the wind far and wide.
Soothing singing and amatory dancing intertwined with strings and pipes,
The Emperor indulged day and night ever wanting more.
Until suddenly war drums from Yuyang had the capital's earth quaking,
Sprung out of tune was Lady Yang's dance in the Rainbow Dress and Feather Robe.

The revolt stormed near bringing smoke and dust to the palace towers,
The Emperor decided to south-west retreat with his cavalry of tens of thousands.
The Emperor's coach with a jade flower flag made way and stops now and again,
West of the capital for mere tens of miles they rode;
Then the army refused to continue course, the Emperor in dilemma had to consent
To the now wailing Lady's execution at once in front of horses for all to see.
Strangled she was, her bejewelled hair pieces were left scattered on the ground,
Jade and golden ornaments that used to adorn her hair.
The Emperor could not the fair lady rescue nor bear to watch,
When he did look back, he wept tears that flowed also blood.
The bleakness lingered in the bitter wind storming the yellow earth sky high,
The retreat continued through alpine passes from the Cloudy to the Sword-like.
The foot of the Emei Mountains in the Shu region used to little traffic see,
Yet lacklustre was the feel of the Emperor's flag and daylight appeared weak.
The waters of Shu were blue and its mountains green,
The Emperor however was day after day consumed by the remembrance of love lost.
At his temporary residence, the moon offered nothing but added to his grieve,
The rain and bells at night rang the sound of his heart broken in pieces.

After moving heaven and earth, the Emperor returned in his dragon coach,
Stopping at where his Lady died, unable to move on, long he lingered.
For beneath the soil of the Mawei Slopes must be where his lady lied,
Though her beautiful face of pure jade might have in vain sacrificed.
The Emperor and his courtiers looked on, their collars damp with tears,
Their loosely reigned horses sauntered eastward towards the capital gates.
The palace gardens and ponds were as they had always been in their comeback,
The hibiscus in the Taiye Pond blossomed, the willows in the Weiyang Mansion thrived;
The hibiscus was like the late Lady's face and the willows her eyebrows,
With such scenery, how could the Emperor not be reminded of the Lady's countenance?
How they had seen together the peach and plum blossoms in the spring breeze,
How they had watched the leaves leave phoenix trees in autumn rain.
The Emperor now resided in the south-western mansion full of autumn vegetation,
Where stairs were covered in reddened leaves and no one would come by to sweep.
The operatic circle students' hair had begun to turn grey,
Eunuchs and maids at the late Lady's mansion had aged and faded away.
The palace had a lonely place become, even fireflies of night could not it enliven,
The Emperor's lament would wear a lone candle to its end on sleepless nights.
Night-hour gongs gonged the start of long nights,
Starry light lighted so bright resembling daybreak time.
Palace roof figurines of mandarin ducks were covered cold in heavy frost,
With whom could the Emperor share the now warmth-lacking kingfisher feather quilt?
In a daze, the passing of the late Lady had been a year in time,
Yet her spirit never once the Emperor's dream entered for a rendezvous.

A Taoist priest from Lingqiong of the region of Shu,
Claimed to with his sincere and pure faith dead spirits reach;
As the Emperor seemed forever engrossed in the remembrance of the late Lady,
The priest was summoned to seek attentively for her spirit.
In lightening speed he glided in thin air and navigated the clouds,
He searched everywhere in the sky and on the earth but failed to her spirit find;
He exhausted all avenues in heaven and the nether world,
Boundless and vast as they were, he could not her existence bring to light.
Then he heard of tales of a celestial mountain in the sea,
That lay in the mid of misty nowhere.
In the mountains amongst clouds of rainbow colours existed delicate architecture,
And there lived many beautiful fairies.
Of them there was a fairy named True Faith, same as the late Lady,
With whom the fairy shared much similar snow-white skin and flowery face.
The priest came to the gate of the golden West Hall to knock on a door of jade,
And asked the heavenly maid and matron to their fairy lady notify.
Upon hearing the arrival of the Emperor's envoy,
The Lady resting behind her canopy of nine flowers was startled and aroused;
She pushed aside her pillow to get dressed, then she hesitated and paced,
Surrounded she was by veils of golden beads and silvery mirror panes.
Her luxuriant mane was lopsided from having just woken up,
She came to the main hall with her crooked laureate unadjusted.
Her clothes and sleeves were fluttering in the breeze,
It was like a scene from the Lady's dance of the Rainbow Dress and Feather Robe.
Her beauty is marred by loneliness with her tears in streams,
Muck like a pear flower blooming after the rain.
She gazed at the priest in silence to her gratitude to the Emperor convey,
Since parting they could not each other's voice hear nor visage behold.
Their warmth and love were left behind in the Mansion of Morning Sun,
Her days in the fairy court were long and indefinitely prolonged was time.
When she looked back to the temporal world,
She could not see Changan the capital but dusty and misty skies.
What remained of the bygone days were two keepsakes,
A jewellery casket and a golden hairpin for the priest to the Emperor take.
One half of the hairpin and one tray of the casket she would keep,
Breaking the pin and the box into parts;
She hoped the Emperor's love would be as unflinching as their pledge,
So they could be reunited in heaven or on earth in another life.
Upon bidding farewell to the Emperor's emissary she reminded him repeatedly,
To relay to the Emperor a poem wherein contained their secret oath,
Once on the seventh night of the seventh moon in the Hall of Eternity,
When no one was around they whispered words of love in the depth of night:
"In heaven above let us be one-winged birds and only in pairs fly,
On earth let us be neighbouring trees with our branches intertwined."
Yet even if eternal heaven and earth ever had an end,
Never-ending would be this couple's immortal regret.
    </property>
        </label>
      </list_item>
    </scroll_view>
    <scroll_bar_d name="bar" x="right" y="0" w="12" h="100%" value="0"/>
  </list_view>
  <button name="close" x="center" y="bottom:10" w="50%" h="30" text="close"/>
</window>
